<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A copie of the speache: made by the mathematicall lecturer unto the worshipfull companye present. At the house of the worshipfull M. Thomas Smith, dwelling in Gracious Street: the 4. of Nouember, 1588. T. Hood.</title>
            <author>Hood, Thomas, fl. 1582-1598.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1588</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 26 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03573</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13694</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108609</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844266</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844266</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9063</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03573)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9063)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 548:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A copie of the speache: made by the mathematicall lecturer unto the worshipfull companye present. At the house of the worshipfull M. Thomas Smith, dwelling in Gracious Street: the 4. of Nouember, 1588. T. Hood.</title>
                  <author>Hood, Thomas, fl. 1582-1598.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Edward Allde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1588]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>B4 torn, with some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mathematics --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Aaron McCollough</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Aaron McCollough</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9063:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9063:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A COPIE OF THE SPEACHE: MADE by the <hi>Mathematicall</hi> Lecturer, unto the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull Companye preſent.</p>
            <p>At the houſe of the Worſhipfull <hi>M. Thomas Smith, dwelling</hi> in Gracious Street: the 4. of <hi>Nouember, 1588.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>T. <hi>Hood</hi>
            </p>
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London by <hi>Edward Allde.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="oration">
            <pb facs="tcp:9063:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9063:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Auſpicante Deo,</hi> 4. <hi>Nouembris</hi> 1588.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Knowe not Right woorſhipfull, and Gentlemen of ſinguler ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation, whether this preſent exerciſe which now we haue in hand doth breed in me a greter cauſe of ioy, or feare. When I conſider with my ſelfe the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious mind of ill diſpoſed men, who thinke no boate well row<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed wherin they want an oare, I cannot be but toucht with feare. Againe, when as I call to minde the great commoditie that wil henceforth ariſe vnto our Realm in that this day there is a platforme laied for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter increace of the Mathematicall ſcience, a ſcience neuer worthely to be commended, then doo I begin to be ſomewhat glad, yea openly to confeſſe what ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I doo: I triumph in deed and leape for ioy. But whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I ſee the burthen of the thing to lye in my necke, and my ſelfe to ſit in ſo enuied a place, then dooth my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer feare returne, and euery ioynt well nigh begin to ſhake. Againe when ſitting in this ſeate although en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uied, I caſt mine eye about to euerye corner of this Roome, and ſée as yet none other here, but either ſuch as doo deſire to learne, and therfore cannot but wiſhe me well, whome they haue choſen their inſtructor, or ſuch as are already learned, and therefore néedes muſt loue the thing whoſe woorthines they knowe, and alſo the profeſſors of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, I féele my ioy renued a freſhe. The which my ioye, Right woorſhipfull that it maye
<pb facs="tcp:9063:3"/>
continue ſtill, till you your ſelues héere preſent, ſhall miniſter occaſion otherwiſe (which your yéeres, diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, conſtancie, and wiſdome perſwade me you will neuer doo) I humbly requeſt ſuch fauourable attenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and good will to the ende of my ſpéeche, as you haue giuen the beginning. The which becauſe I will not haue it ouer long, I will ſet my ſelfe certain limmets and bounds which I will not paſſe, deuiding it into <hi>2.</hi> ſeuerall parts. The one ſhall concearne the occaſion of this exerciſe begun, the other the commoditie of the ſame: of theſe in as ſhort a manner as I maye. It is no ſecret Right woorſhipfull to any of you all, for we haue ſéene them on our coaſte, and heard the thunder of their ſhot, in how cruell manner the proud diſdayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full inſolent Spaniard of late daies hath threatned our Cuntrie, Quéene and Citie, with fire and ſwoord, and whatſoeuer outragious torment elſe their villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous mind could woorſe inuent. The Citizens of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don duetifull to their Prince, to their Cuntrie louing, and careful of the Citie: made ready preſently for their defence a band of men, in number not great, yet for the time ſufficient, til farther danger called for a freſh ſupplie. The men thus leuied required Captaines, for what is the bodie without an heade, or the Schollers without a Maiſter, or ſouldiers wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting ſuch as might inſtruct them in feates of warre? The Citizens, cheefly thoſe, who both for their wiſdom, and experience were beſt able to iudge, and for their fatherly care they haue moſt prouident to foreſée what kinde of gouernement is beſt for this Citie, thoſe Citizens I ſay did think it good to chooſe out Captaines among themſelues, to whom they might commit this military care. Yet leaſt they ſhould preſume too much vpon their owne deuiſe, or raſhly ſeem to contemne the warlike pollicie of other
<pb facs="tcp:9063:3"/>
men, they acquaint her Maieſtie with the thing. Her Maieſtie as ſhe is alwaies glad to gratifie her ſubiects in their honeſt petitions, ſo in this ſhe ſhewed her ſelfe willing to ſatiſfie their mindes, being induced thereto by the graue aduiſe of her honourable Councell. Heer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon, theſe and diuers other woorſhipfull Gentlemen, were choſen Captains, their Souldiers were trained, and trained in ſuch ſorte as fewe indéede or none were better, ſo the euent enſuing did declare. For this we ſée, Right woorſhipfull, that enuie neuer followeth the worſer ſorte. <hi>Summa petit liuor</hi> ſaith the Poet, <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flantquae altiſsima venti,</hi> and what néedeth diſgrace where the thing is bad? Our Captaines were ſoughte to be diſgraced, I néede ſaye no more, iudge you your ſelues now what men they were, ſeeinge enuies blaſt dooth alwaies beate the higheſt hilles. But be it ſo to auoide contention, &amp; becauſe compariſons are alwaies odious, our Captains themſelues are willing to deny their deſerte. They acknowledge that, which their ill willers obiect, they haue not encamped in open feelde, nor beſieged townes, nor raiſed ſconſes, nor battered walles, nor burnte and ſpoyled Cities as they haue doone, for why? neither their yéeres, nor calling, nor trade of life hath ſo required: Yet haue they vertuous and valiant mindes, they loue their Cuntrie, they ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor their Prince, they care for this Citie, and they haue knowledge not to be contemned, till tract of time affoordeth experience. Now that theſe their vertues may increace, and alſo their learning be enlarged, and they more fit for experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to come, it pleaſed them (di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers graue, wiſe and pollitick men, giuing encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment therunto) for their priuate inſtruction to erecte a lecture for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mathematicall ſcience, a knowledge moſt conuenient for militarie men. But héer ſome men per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happes
<pb facs="tcp:9063:4"/>
will ſay, what néedeth this coſt? what? thoſe famous Captaines of ours now in the low Cuntries, or thoſe of ancient time before, whoſe notable prow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſe is left in writing, were they trained up in this kind of learning which you haue named, and highlye com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mende? In trueth Right woorſhipfull it is hard to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouch this of all them that are and haue beene intitled with this warlike name, yet am I not ignorant what to anſwere. I acknowledge, and confeſſe, that there haue beene many of noble vertue and excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t mindes, who without learning by their deuine &amp; heauenlye na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture alone haue ſhewed themſelues worthy &amp; valiant men yea alſo I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deſcend to this, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> oftentimes nature without learning, is more auailable to vertue and renowne, then learning without nature, yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding this I muſt needs affirm, that when to a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and excellent inclination of nature there is ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the deuiſe and helpe which learning breedeth, then ſpringeth vp that ſinguler and peereleſſe man, whome you and I may better in minde concieue, then vtter in woords. Suche was <hi>Scipio Affrycanus</hi> the Romaine Captaine, a mortall God, ſuche was <hi>Cato</hi> that valiant and learned olde man, and many more, who queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe if they coulde haue receiued no helpe by learning, either in attaining to vertue, or enlarging their name: they woulde neuer haue followed the ſtudie thereof. Thus haue you bréeflye heard y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe why this lecture was ordained and for whome, with the anſwere made to an obiection concerning the ſame. It followeth now Right woorſhipfull and curteous auditors, to diſplaye the commodities of our profeſſion namely of <hi>Aſtrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, Arithmeticke,</hi> and <hi>Geometrie:</hi> conteined vnder the title of the mathematicall artes, which thing I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently would enter into, were it not that I had a few
<pb facs="tcp:9063:4"/>
woordes to vtter concerning my ſelf, for it may be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture that ſome of you doo wonder w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your ſelues conſidering your vniuerſities abound and ſwarm with learned doctors, why I eſpecially by degree but a Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of arte, ſhould occupie this place, who neither for yéeres, nor learning, nor experience, ſéeme any waye comparable vnto them. What then? am I bolder then they all? no forſooth. What am I more offici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous then the reſt? no neither, I am not ſo deſirous of that praiſe, that I woulde withdrawe it from other men. But thus it is: other men though indéede better learned then I and of higher degrée, yet ſéeing the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie of the place, and not being called theru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to: withold the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues. I not like to be ſo much enuied, as being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour in degrée: haue ventured on the thing, moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer thoſe parties haue requeſted it at my handes who both for acquaintance and great good will, and woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull countenance might haue commaunded a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thing, whoſe pleaſure for ſo much as I would not withſtand it, nor neglect their requeſt, nor refuſe their good turne, I haue ſubmitted my neck to the burthen. Which though it ſéeme too heauy for me to beare, yet ſhall you not ſee me ſhrinke thereat, whilſte you your ſelues are willing to learne, which ſo long you ought to be willing to doo, vntill it repente you of the profit.</p>
            <p>This proffit the better to vnderſtand what it will be, I will now haſten to the laſt parte of my ſpeache, requeſting héerin alſo your attentiue eare, although I thinke it a néedleſſe requeſt, in that you haue ſo fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably heard me hetherto. Wherin Right woorſhipfull I will labour to be bréefe, I ſaye I will labour to be bréefe, for that I knowe the woorthineſſe of theſe artes to be ſuch, that it is an harder matter to finde an ende in commending the ſame, then a beginning to their
<pb facs="tcp:9063:5"/>
praiſe. For what ſoeuer ſeuerall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendations there are in other things in this profeſſion: they all concurre and méete togeather. If either antiquitie of any arte may magnifie the ſame, or the profeſſors therof bring credit therto, or the wonderfull effects and ſtrange de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſes extoll the thing, or the ſubiect matter ſet foorthe the praiſe, then ſhall the mathematicks ſurpaſſe them all: they were inuented before all other, imbraſed by Kinges and wiſeſt men, ſtrange in deuiſes and effects, and for the ſubiect matter they haue the world. Their antiquitie is fet from our creation.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Nam cum prona ſpectent animalia caetera terram</l>
               <l>Os homini ſublime dedit, caelumque videre</l>
               <l>Iuſsit, et erectos ad ſidera tolle re vultus.</l>
            </q>
            <p>To this intent were our eyes, and bodies fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med as you ſee, that not looking groueling on the ground as ſenceleſſe beaſtes, but lifting vp our face to heauen we might beholde, and in beholding learne the wonderfull miſteries contained therein. For Right Woorſhipfull: there is more required of vs men co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning heauen, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the only view of the outward frame: the beaſtes themſelues can view the thing, they can beholde it as well as wee, but wee muſt treade the footſteppes of <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Seth</hi> his Sonne, whoſe ſtudy was continuall in theſe thinges, yea they had ſuche a care therof, that knowing the proffit exceeding greate and foreſéeing both the flood to come, and alſo the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming of the worlde by fier, they left the ſecrets of their artes engrauen curiouſly in two Pillers, one of Bricke, the other of braſſe, that if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world were burnt the brick might laſt, if it were drowned, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> braſſe might continue the perpetuall memorye of that which they knew. It is too long to runne through all thoſe men, whoſe affection was ſinguler to theſe kinde of ſtudies</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:9063:5"/>
               <hi>Abraham</hi> is renowned for his knowledge therein, and <hi>Iacob</hi> alſo, whoſe ſtaffe we vſe. The <hi>Egiptians</hi>
learning theſe artes of <hi>Abraham,</hi> founde afterwarde ſuche ſingularitie therein, that it was a decree for euer with them, that none ſhould gouerne among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as King, that had no inſight in this learning, whoſe Lawe the <hi>Perſians</hi> alſo followed. From <hi>Egipt:</hi> it flowed ouer <hi>Affricke</hi> like <hi>Nilus</hi> floud, and after went ouer ſea into <hi>Greece,</hi> from <hi>Greece</hi> it was tranſlated to <hi>Rome,</hi>
from <hi>Rome</hi> to <hi>Germany, Fraunce,</hi> and <hi>Spaine,</hi> and now at length after many yéeres <hi>England</hi> dooth lend it a liſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning eare, and as I hope will yéelde it alſo a louing hart. At <hi>Rome <hi>Iulius Caeſar</hi>
               </hi> made the Calender which we vſe, in <hi>Greece <hi>Plato</hi>
               </hi> by that arte did ſtay the plague in doubling the aulter of <hi>Apollo.</hi> In <hi>Affricke</hi> King <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las</hi>
did ſo toyle therin. that the Poets laid the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in his necke, and made him as a piller to holde it vp. <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chimedes</hi>
plaied the Deuill therby in the Romain hoſt, and kepte them all at ſuch a baye, that they durſt not come neere <hi>Syracuſa,</hi> neither by Land nor yet by Sea, <hi>Dionyſius</hi> the King he ſent for <hi>Plato</hi> to be his Maiſter in this ſcience, and made bonfiers for ioy of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, <hi>Alfonſus</hi> King of <hi>Aragon</hi> ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t a mighty ſumme of money héerin, and maketh vs beholding to him ſtill and ſhall be for euer. <hi>Ptolomiè</hi> tooke ſuch paines heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, that the whole worlde enioyes his trauell. If then Right woorſhipfull, the ſtudentes in this ſcience were ſuch famous men, imagine the excellency of the ſtudie, which alſo they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended vnto vs by ſinguler works. I meane not your Cathedrall Churches, or place of Exchange, or other ſtatelye buildinges whatſoeuer, whoſe ſtilleſt ſtone is the ſounding Trumpet of this profeſſion, but they left behinde them manifolde other rare deuiſes, to ſight wonderfull, incredible to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eare, yet to eare and ſight excéeding pleaſant. Suppoſe, for
<pb facs="tcp:9063:6"/>
what cannot the minde deuiſe? ſuppoſe I ſay, that ouer your heade there flewe a Doue, not ſuche a feathered fowle as commonly we kéep, but a Doue of wood, ſuch a one as <hi>Archytas</hi> made. Put caſe you ſaw héer <hi>Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canes</hi>
treuets, which made of Iron could fight alone: and ſet them ſelues in battell raye, retiring and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching orderly. What if you ſaw <hi>Daedalus</hi> in the ayre? or <hi>Archimedes</hi> Sphere turning alone? would you not wonder at theſe things? Yes no doubt, and wondring, thirſt after the knowledge of that arte, which daylye affoordes ſuch ſtrange conceites.</p>
            <p>Theſe be no fables that I tell, our preſent age af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth them true. Who hath not heard of the brazen Cocke in <hi>Strasborowe</hi> towne, as I remember, which croweth alowd <hi>3.</hi> times a day: wherin the heauenlye Orbes doo moue alone? Who hath not ſéene our Clock in <hi>Paules,</hi> or ſuch ſmall péeces of woorke as this? which being but ſmall in regarde of the reſt, bring great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations to theſe artes. Héere againe me thinke, I heare one ſay, indéed theſe toyes delight mens eyes, but I deſire to ſée ſome vſe, or ſome commoditie fit for a common weale: this queſtion Right woorſhipfull, I could anſwere with an other, altogether as fooliſhe as it. What profit hath the Diamond on your finger, for which you gaue an hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred pound? you can not anſwer me at a bluſh, except you aleadge your pleaſure alone. But I will not croſſe this obiection thus, I will an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere directly therunto, although the pleaſure might ſuffiſe, as being a ſtudye pleſant in youth, delightfull to age, beautifull in proſperitie, reléeuing our aduerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and yéelding vs comfort, it pleaſureth at home, it hindreth not abroad, it watcheth with vs, and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelleth with vs vp and downe, and dooth vs ſeruice e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery where. The minde is able Right woorſhipfull, to conceiue that which the bodily eye cannot ſée, the eye
<pb facs="tcp:9063:6"/>
can beholde more then the tung can expreſſe, yet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe with your minde, and caſt your ſight about, and trye if you can either ſpye with your eye, or thinke in your minde what thing is frée from the vſe of theſe artes. Look vp if you pleaſe to the heauen aboue, or turne your eye downe to earth beneath, or round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to the wandering Sea, thinke on your warres, and traffique abroad, or other your priuate affaires at home, your buſines at home, your wares abroad, your traffique beyond ſea, the earth beneath you, the Sea about you, the heauen aboue you is fully fraught with the praiſe héerof. In heauen Aſtronomye dooth raigne as Queene, commaunding all the ſecrets thereof, and laying them open to our eyes. Yet Aſtronomye is but a parte of this ſcience, whoſe proffit notwithſtanding is wonderfull greate. What can be compared to the knowledge of God, which is the butte and end of our creation? next to the ordenary meanes of our inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I meane his woord, the arte of aſtronomye dooth cheefely bréede the knowledge of him. Firſt in conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the number of the heauens, which being <hi>10.</hi> are ſo cunningly wrought and knit togeather, that the hand of man is not able to counterfeite the woorſte of them all, without ſome blemiſh, either ſwelling outward, or dented in, their rowndneſſe is ſuch, ſo precize, ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, ſo correſpondent to it ſelfe. If then the faſhion be ſo ſtrange, and broedeth this proffit, what maye we conceiue of the wonderfull courſe, which rolling about without any reſte, is an higher ſteppe to the foreſaide knowledge. Of theſe <hi>10.</hi> Spheres or Orbes, there are not two whoſe naturall courſe precizelye bendeth one manner of way. Some runne from Eaſt to Weſt, and others againe from Weſt to Eaſt, an other in trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling manner from North to South, reuerſed backe from South to North. The Nethermoſt <hi>7.</hi> from weſt
<pb facs="tcp:9063:7"/>
to Eaſt in ſuch a ſundrie and manifolde courſe, that neither the one is like the other, nor in many yéeres ſcarſe like themſelues, yet all ſo certaine in their race, that neither the time dooth bréed an error, nor yet their number a confuſion. Which conſtancie of courſe being wel known to <hi>Dionyſius Areopagita</hi> an heathen man, it made him crye out when our Sauiour Chriſte was nailed to the Croſſe, (though he him ſelfe were then in <hi>Egipt</hi>) that then, either the God of nature did ſuffer, or the frame of this worlde did breake a ſunder: becauſe againſt the order and time of naturall courſe, he ſawe the Moone eclipſe the Sunne. Séeing then <hi>Aſtronomye</hi>
leadeth vs to the knowledge of God, that were proffit enough if it had no more: but this commoditie is not alone, for as this is the welfare of the ſoule: ſo dooth it woork our bodies good: as phiſick can witnes ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, which taking care of this our bodye, can warrant vs nothing without this arte. For if it dooth not deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently obſerue the face of heauen in miniſtring poti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or opening vaines, it maye ſerue vs as <hi>Paris</hi> did <hi>Achilles</hi> at <hi>Troy,</hi> whoſe pricke in the héele did pearſe his hart. What ſhall I ſay of Nauigation the chéefeſt piller of your gaine? how much dooth Aſtronomy helpe therin? whoſe launching foorth and haling in, and reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe courſe both too and fro is ſurelye guided by this heauenly arte, though Sea dooth roare, and windes doo rage, and heauen and earth ſhould méete together. As for the tilling of the ground or whatſoeuer elſe the Cuntrie dooth, it is as much for it to want this Arte, as <hi>Vulcanes</hi> forge to lack his fier, or <hi>Apelles</hi> ſhop his cullours and oyle: I would not haue you meaſure eche thing by the price, for commonlye ſchollers are not co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetous men. There is among you a little booke, the Almanacke I mean vſually bought for a peny or two, if it were wanting but a time, I geſſe it would be
<pb facs="tcp:9063:7"/>
woorth a pound. Right woorſhipfull I wil vſe your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience a little longer, becauſe I ſée you giue ſuch at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiue eare: You haue heard what great commodity Aſtronomy yeeldeth, being but a parte of the Mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall ſcience, there are other two as good as it, harken alſo what profit they bring, Arithmeticke namely teaching the art of number, and Geometrie the knowledge of meaſuring wel. Beleeue me, for why I ſpeake the thing I knowe, being daylye conuerſant in thoſe parts, and hauing conference with many me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, there is no calling whatſoeuer that can want the aide of one of theſe. Perhaps you will except Aſtronomie, becauſe the heauen ſéemeth very high beyond the reach of rule and compaſſe. Our Globes and Spheres and celeſtiall draughts, which héere we haue, will witnes the falſehood of that exception, wherein eche ſeuerall ſtarre is ſo truelye prickt that they miſſe not an haire of their naturall place. Then if Geometrie reache ſo high that it can iuſtly meaſure the Cope of heauen: no doubt on earth it performeth moſt excellent thinges. Let Geographie witneſſe in vniuerſall Mappes, let Topographie witneſſe in ſeuerall Cardes, let Hydro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphie witneſſe in the Mariners plat, you your ſelues may witneſſe in Martiall affaires, let the Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner witneſſe in planting his ſhot, witneſſe the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veior in meaſuring land, witneſſe all thoſe, that labor in mines, and thoſe that practiſe conueying of water, whoſe ſkill being tolde vs, we would ſcarſely beleeue it, were it not lying at our doores. The Lawyer thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth him ſelfe cunning enough to handle his caſe, and therfore would laugh, if he ſhould héere, that he ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in néed of our profeſſion, yet haue I knowne his ſentence reclaimed by one of my coate. Diuinitie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth matter of ſaluation, and nothing is ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in the woord of God, yet can it not be expounded
<pb facs="tcp:9063:8"/>
without theſe artes, elſe let them deſcribe the feaſte of Eaſter, or iuſtefie the hiſtorye of the three wiſe men. If you your ſelues were not Merchant men, I would tel you what proffit you reape héerby, but your dayly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perince ſaueth me that labour. The Scholler in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of his Poet muſt haue this helpe, or els perhaps he may quickly be poſed. The Hiſtoriographer muſt not want theſe artes, nor he that readeth the hiſtorie penned, or elſe their labour and light maye be loſt. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> It was the ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce Right woorſhipfull auditors of <hi>Plato</hi> the wiſe ſet ouer his Schoole, wherby he forbad them the entrance in, that were no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t capable of this learning, for as it is pretely, ſo it is truely ſaide by one <hi>Vt ignis aurum, ita Mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mataeca ingenium,</hi> The Mathematickes are vnto the wit, as fire is to the golde, and he that in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure is not capable therof, is fitter for a ſtie, then for a ſtudie. Perſwade your ſelues Captains of excellent hope, for now I turne my ſpéeche to you, for whoſe commoditie this thing is intended, perſwade your ſelues I ſaye, that there is ſome notable thing in this kinde of ſtudie, that is not common to other artes, els could it not breed ſuch exceeding ioy in the louers ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as we ſee it dooth. <hi>Thales</hi> the Philoſopher offred vp an Oxe for ioy, and <hi>Plato</hi> an hundred hauing found out certaine Geometricall concluſions. <hi>Archimedes</hi>
ſifting out the Goldeſmithes deceipte in making of King <hi>Hiero</hi> his Crown, could not contain him ſelf for ioy, but ran as he was ſtark naked through the ſtréet <hi>Ariſtippus</hi> ſuffering ſhipwracke on the coaſt of <hi>Rhodes</hi>
found deſcribed in the ſande Geometricall figures, wherin he took ſuch ſinguler comforte, that forgetting his loſſe, and cauſe of ſorrow: he cryed out thus vnto his fellowes, be of good cheere my mates quoth he, for loe I ſée the footeſteppes of men. If then noble Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines
<pb facs="tcp:9063:8"/>
and louing Schollers, (for now I am bolde to vſe that name) If the commodities of our profeſſion be ſo great as nothing more, if the pleaſure be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out compariſon, if theſe be the footſteppes of men wherin you muſt treade, whoſe very ſight may coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teruaile your ſorrow, if you haue a care of your hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable name, if you thinke it a fowle diſgrace for want of knowledge to be circumuented, as <hi>Haniball</hi> was by <hi>Fabivs Maximus,</hi> or as <hi>Cyrus</hi> the King by <hi>Tomiris</hi>
the Quéene: If it be the hazarde of your life and name in ſkaling a forte to bring a Ladder too ſhorte by the halfe, as King <hi>Phillip</hi> did, wherby he caſt away all his men: if you loathe to haue your inferiour Souldiers triumph ouer you for want of arte, as <hi>Palamedes</hi> did ouer <hi>Agamemnon</hi> the King, begin better ſéen in mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhalling his men: to be ſhorte, If you thinke it a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thing, to compaſſe the worlde, and returne again enriched with golde, or if you tender your credit in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reſpect which ought to be more deer then gold, now haue an eſpeciall care vnto the ſame. Let not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thing begun to your honor be intermitted to your diſgrace, ſo many woorſhipfull men bearing witneſſe therof, but buckle your ſelues to purchaſe knowledge, that by your endeuour out of this place, as out of the Gréekiſh Horſe at <hi>Troy,</hi> many woorthy, wiſe, and learned Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines may procéede. Your coſt is ſmall, your paines as little, for all the labour ſhall be mine, your profit greate: your comfort more, there wantes but will, which if you bring, vpon my credit, God going before whom I beſéeche to bleſſe our ſtudies, you ſhall not thinke your time <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> but be beholding as to this Gentlem<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> place, ſo vnto me for taking paines.</p>
            <trailer>Dixi.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
